hey I'm going I don't normally read I
generally try to speak from the heart
but today I'm going to be reading a
intro so the idea cafe is space for
people to come to exactly as they are
and share their unique lived experiences
when we are able to connect and truly
see one another a whole new way of being
on this planet is possible virginal II
planned for a light and easy question to
start us off
but I also unintentionally scheduled our
first idea cafe on a day that is neither
light nor easy for many people in order
to honor the day I want to ask our
participants to share about the question
where were you 18 years ago and allow
the individual to decide what to share
about that time period of their life
social media has become a place of
superficial interactions most of the
time and the idea cafe aims to be the
opposite this means we are sometimes
going to share raw emotions and be
present for other people in whatever
state they show up in the moment
social media is generally designed as a
platform where few speak and many listen
we are creating a platform that flips
this into everyone participating in the
conversation however right now we are
broadcasting on YouTube we aim to
showcase that everyone's story and
experiences are worthy on this
particular day I just want to
acknowledge that our stories are not
more important and should not be
elevated above those who are directly
impacted by the events that unfolded 18
years ago however the events were also
witnessed globally through media
coverage and we all have a story on how
we were impacted at that time all
stories matter all people are worthy and
we are here to participate in an
intimate conversation that the world may
bear witness to this is a somewhat
strange medium to do this on but I
believe it is happening today in this
way for a reason
when challenging events unfolds in real
time in the future our platform the idea
cafe will be a space where everyone can
go to be seen and heard and share their
emotions in real time with real people
this is how the world grows and heals
together
now I invite us to take a deep breath
arrive in our bodies and share what we
feel comfortable and called to we will
each take turns sharing for
approximately five minutes on this
week's question the rest of us will be
listening and at the end after we have
all shared we can each share briefly
what we have received from others
sharing question this week is where were
you 18 years ago and now I'm just going
to add I don't know I'm in my classroom
how are you good how are you doing and
what I hear you've added some icon so we
actually can't bear your name nor your
pronoun it's on the MS optimism miss
optimism okay and you go by she her
sorry she heard four pronouns yeah
Shan Shan I don't know how to use that
as a pronoun but okay alright and I'm
just gonna unmute Charlotte as well
and so who would like to start I think I
already said where the question is yeah
who would like to start where were you
18 years ago not also mentioned I'm will
mute the other people who aren't going
while we are well we're talking while
the person's talking I can go if needed
awesome
sure so I was on my summer vacation from
University and I was working in Greece
and it was the first summer I had done
anything like that and I was
experiencing so much freedom to be
myself and I was working on the beach
just a average afternoon as they always
were and suddenly this little old Greek
man came running down to the beach just
like frantic just needing us like
wanting us
we had no idea what was going on we
didn't speak Greek he didn't speak
English and he was just like come with
us come with me come with me I had no
idea what was happening and he took us
to his davana and out the back was this
little old TV screen and it was just on
a Greek Channel so we couldn't even hear
the commentary but they were just
repeatedly playing the initial footage
of the planes going into the Twin Towers
and it was so fascinating the without
the commentary we had no idea exactly
what had happened
or why it was happening and the stories
that we were all adding to this video a
common video footage that we were
watching without actually knowing
anything in hindsight was very
interesting to to reflect on that and
then with a very slow dial-up internet
connection I remember somebody looking
on some news websites and knew I think
we were looking on the the BBC the
English news website British and sort of
the breaking news the breaking news more
and more information coming in and the
other piece that yeah just comes up to
me now remembering it was the it was
just coming to the end at the summit we
were all meant to be flying home now
jobs out there were like coming into the
end for the summer season the tourists
were closing down and we had no idea if
we would be able to fly home they shut
down all international travel for I
can't remember how long it was and just
realizing their significance of this and
how I'd lived in such a privileged place
of not experiencing anything like that
before they grew up in London in the
1980s so I was very aware of the IRA and
have been indirectly impacted by a lot
of their activity
but to think that I can get home to my
like privileged land of England was a
very very strange sensation and yeah and
they they call us on a flight well it
was reroute it all over the place and
minimal luggage and hand luggage and no
liquids and just people saying like this
is going to change the world this is
going to change the world and then the
story's just coming out more and more
and the panic from people who had
friends and family in New York I'm just
all the different side stories that
would be coming out of both the impact
on the world the impact on us even in
England the understanding the this is
just maybe the tip of the iceberg of an
iceberg I certainly didn't even know
existed was yeah just this is big and I
have no idea how big it is what I mean
gonna be looking at and I'm actually
flying somewhere tomorrow and I want to
just take hand luggage I'm just away for
the weekend and it even just struck me
again of like oh I can't just grab my
machete and shower bottles shower gel
bottles I need to know you it's like
eighteen years later even something like
can I take my shampoo on a flight with
me just minor but yeah knock on it's
still there so yeah but I think you'll
always stay with me watching watching
the footage unfold on this Greek
television channel but with no
understanding a Greek to have the
commentary of what was happening and how
that's slowly unfolded and yeah
those stories getting deeper and deeper
I think that's always gonna stay with me
so I am unmuting getting used to stream
yard I'm just a dagger back um miss
optimism do you want to go next or would
you like me to go next I can hear you
you want to go now so unfortunately went
myself across the Pacific
if my mic muted and then I can't see
someone's face so the people who aren't
talking I'm actually gonna remove from
the stream completely so I think it'll
work better I'll still be able to see
you just you know that you are still on
camera but I cannot hear you all it
might be because you would you if you
have a mic you can hear you if you want
to share your story then we can hear you
you can hear me yeah so how about you
share your story and I'm gonna remove us
from here so we'll still be able to well
I can't hear you but 18 years ago I'm a
native New Yorker so 18 years ago I was
actually leaving my house I was living
on 2469 Clayton Powell Boulevard and a
Adam Clayton Powell Boulevard it's about
a 15 minute train ride about 20 minutes
car by to wear the towel was were so I
said okay well I'm gonna go downstairs
I'm gonna get my butter roll and get my
coffee and just make life you know
normal as possible so as I'm going
downstairs on 8 o'clock or so I order my
normal and I proceeded to just go about
my business so I talked to the store
owner as we always did and exchanged
pleasantries and then I went to my
building and then I decided I was going
to see on the roof so in New York it's
not that uncommon to sit on the roof and
just you know either bask in the Sun or
just relax look at the birds enjoy the
way
whatever it is that you do so I said oh
my gosh I totally forgot to take money
out of the ATM let me go back downstairs
take money out and then I'll go ahead
with the rest of my day while I was on
the roof I kept looking and I said what
is going on downtown because again I was
only on 146 Street about 80 blocks or so
away from the World Trade Center
now does one I wouldn't igress and share
of this as a child growing up from
Queens our balcony faced the entire New
York skyline and I always tried myself
by saying I live in the greatest city in
the world with the most prettiest and
aesthetically pleasing skyline ever and
I bragged about that so when I moved to
MIT it wasn't so much the same so I just
enjoyed what I was able to get like part
a Chrysler Building for the Empire State
Building and the glimpse of the World
Trade Center so I'm watching I said wow
they must be filming like a Will Smith
movie or something because there's a lot
of smoke a lot of planes a lot of things
like happening and I had no idea what
was going on once again we didn't have
cell phones with FaceTime we didn't have
cell phones with you know the abilities
and capabilities to talk it was just
like that little AOL man buffering and
running and buffering and running so I
go downstairs and I went to go to the
ATM machine and the ATM machine kept
flashing it was a flashing that's oh
that's weird I don't go to the one down
the block so I would someone 144th the
143rd the one on one hundred thirty nine
the 150th and I said this is so weird
that everything what ATM machine I'm
going to is flickering every last one of
them don't work something is absolutely
wrong so go back to the bodega and I
said I said you know uh what is going on
I can't get money out he said we'll try
my machine now no one went to his
machine because his machine had like
this huge fee to take money out so I go
to his his ATM and again same thing
flashing ever ever ever so I said
something is terribly wrong and when I
turned around he and others were just
standing there with their mouths
open so I said what's going on would
happen you know did someone die like
what happened and he said this is not
gonna be a good day for anybody and he
wouldn't say anything else I said okay
whatever I go upstairs and that's a Roy
you won't believe it none of the ATM
machines are working my cell phone is
not working I don't know what's going on
and he said look at this watch the news
so I said what am I looking at I said oh
that must be the Will Smith film that
they're filming downtown he said this
isn't a film this is real and I could
not believe what I was seeing and I
couldn't call family because all the
phone lines were down my families were
in Queens
my family were in Queens Brooklyn and
the Bronx couldn't get in contact with
anybody and then went ahead and I'm
sorry they were just missing I went
ahead and tried to get in touch with
anybody and I could not get anybody at
all whatsoever so now I'm panicking and
now we're going to channel 2 channel 4
channel 5 channel 7 channel 9 channel 11
every single channel had the same
disturbing pictures it just blew my mind
so that's where I was 18 years ago 18
years later I tried to teach my students
that although they may not have been
born or they were young to still treat
people kindly no matter what they look
like to love one another no matter what
they look like and tried and when I tell
them about my situation and what
happened with 911 they're just an
amazement more so because of Technology
purposes but they just couldn't believe
something inhuman like that could happen
so that's my story thank you for sharing
that and I know you can't hear us if you
go on to the YouTube channel you can but
right now I'm gonna talk so I love both
of you and well for myself remember how
to do this
all right so much like Charlotte I was
traveling I was I think week - not even
week - it was my first few days in
Australia I was planning on being there
for six months and I was staying with a
friend in
Bondi Beach and so because of the time
difference it was actually nighttime and
evening and he had went to bed with his
girlfriends and for some reason I turned
on that I turned on the TV which I
normally wouldn't have done and what I
saw was the the Twin Towers and the
plane hitting it like in real time and I
was like guys you need to get up you
need to come and you need to see this
you need to see what is happening
there's something big going on and
because I even had the underlining
thought like is this a movie is it
something else going on but there was
something in me that was like this is
big this is huge and in real-time we
watched we watched it unfold for for
about an hour and I remember being much
like Charlotte I was I was far away I'd
had this experience of traveling
internationally and traveling back home
was a completely night and day different
experience I had to remove my shoes like
30 times in the airport but what stuck
with me was the next day walking around
Sydney and the global mourning that was
going on like everyone knew how big it
was and even though we were a world away
and in Sydney there aren't that many
Americans there's a ton of Canadians a
ton of British but there aren't that
many Americans and yet we could all
still feel this monumentous event and it
was this like quiet over the city even
though again I was as in other worlds
away and then watching the events that
unfolded over the next couple months as
I traveled throughout Australia like I
remember the war being declared on
Afghanistan well I was in Byron Bay and
I don't remember so much happen while I
was there but I mean it was 18 years ago
and I've had a few brain things since
then but having the experience of
travelling home and hearing people's
stories and I didn't even think about
the difference in technology but yeah
travelling in Australia I wasn't talking
to people on video chat I was using a
phone card and calling people from a
payphone so I could connect with people
back home and because of the time
difference and the distance but but
still feeling this monumental event that
the world was was griefing
so that was where I was 18 years ago
and now I would love to open it back up
for to share anything that was brought
up as a as other people shared our
common our commonalities and what but it
was I can I can start even though I
ended I was just I found it really
interesting that both Charlotte and I
although I've known you for years we've
never had this conversation because it
doesn't come up very often and that we
were both traveling internationally
which i think is common for you but not
in a very common for me but I was in
Australia where there was English and
you were in like Greece where you didn't
speak the language and the difference
there and then you miss optimism having
um like being there and experiencing
that piece of it that like you weren't
even just like in America you were there
with the ATM's not work you know I'm
guessing they were working in most other
places in the country but just the event
doesn't Angus I mean I think the most
surreal part about that was the most
heartbreaking was the fact that you can
smell what was going on even that far on
146 Street the smoke from about and I'm
just guesstimating I would say from like
maybe a hundred tenth Street and beyond
you could not see anything it was this
thick fume of smoke and it was scary
because we didn't know what it was we
didn't know how far I would travel
people ran aside their homes their
apartments business shut down people
like totally clamped up their windows
because they didn't know what was going
to happen next and I know as primitive
as it sounds we were basically lost
because after a while even the land
mines which was our 90% go to they were
all down so you would just left up to oh
my god what's going to happen next are
they going to come closer is this an
attack on the entire city of New York
and sadly I have friends and family that
worked in that building and even worse
we my um sorority sister to whom is my
best friend she was stuck on the train
during that time directly under what was
going on so I had to impact Charlotte
the trains were just stuck they wouldn't
allow them to move so she said you can
hear the crashing sounds you can hear
screaming she said it was just so
terrifying and in New York City when
your train is stalled you don't want to
hear anything you want to hurry if it
gets where you're going but no one knew
what to tell anybody because no one knew
what was going on and when the tree
finally were able to reverse and go back
towards 125th Street they found out when
they got above-ground what happened and
people like oh my god let me go kiss my
loved ones and my friends because and
hug them because they would I rep it
under one World Trade Center when it all
happened so it was just being there
firsthand and seeing it and smelling it
and not being able to go downtown for
about a month you know was it a
[Music]
commonality unfortunately I think your
connection is broken because I can still
see Charlotte movie remove and most
people don't know there we go like your
mouth was stuck open most people don't
wanna be stuck on streaming like that
well thank you is there anything else
anyone would like to add about this
specific topic about this question for
this week yes thank you
interesting hearing the two perspective
of somebody that was right in New York
City and you know had a best friend that
was fun as it was happening which I just
can't even oh gosh yeah
kinda begin to imagine what that must be
like not knowing that hearing something
happening above you like that when
you're on an underground train
and then our perspectives of being
oceans away the other side of the world
and yet it still ya the impact still
there and that pieces
you mentioned Jubilee about the global
mourning the yeah wherever you are
mmm-hmm buddy knew and hearts were heavy
yes yeah and for me also the like I feel
like this was our generations JK Wow JFK
dying like I remember my mother being
like it happened on her birthday and
like everyone who were they were when
they found out
JFK died or Elvis died or those those
celebrities but this was like such a
huge event that has changed everything
from the time that had occurred and to
connect it with people's personal
stories it's amazing I think this was it
was a great first idea cafe this is what
it's gonna be about is connecting over
real world events and bitter unfolding
as we're occuring in them and it won't
be eighteen years after the fact where
we've had time to process and had time
to see everything coming out of it and
being present for one another so thank
you thank you both in Russia her
internet wasn't quite working she
dropped out but I really appreciate you
both being present for this and and so
next week we will have a different
question I wanted to present the
question now but I think we're gonna
have a conversation about what kind of
question we want and how is I want it
the point of these is to make it
enjoyable for us what do we want to talk
about the witnessing of the world is so
other people can see the power of a
conversation and then also want to join
in
it isn't about presenting it in a way
that's palatable to the masses it's
about creating it so that we enjoy being
part of it and so was I gonna say if
anyone is watching us and let's
participate in this week's question they
can upload a video to the Facebook group
or in the comment section uploaded on
your YouTube video on your YouTube
channel and put a link
in the in the comment section I would
love to hear more stories about how what
you where you were 18 years ago and how
so we can witness each other and be
present for each other because like I
said the beginning that's how we can
heal and grow as a planet and I look
forward to watching this unfold watching
the idea cafe unfolds and so I will I
think we can end it here and say goodbye
and I will see whoever shows up next
week
I just thank you thank you for being
present and for making this area thank
you bye Charlotte bye miss optimism
wherever you are